--==本影片由 CMCT 团队 荣誉出品==--
更多精彩影视 请访问 http://www.cmct.cc
影片压制：死亡骑士　字幕调校：水至清　招募Q号：76846146
黑暗中 你能听得到女人的哭泣
婴儿的嚎啕
男人的呐喊
有人祈求获救
有人祈求速死
但更多人以为诸神已离弃
天地万物陷入永恒的黑暗
小普林尼 公元79年
片名：庞贝末日
北不列颠尼亚 公元62年
凯尔特马族的反叛
总督要重开这些贸易路线
The Governor wants these trade routes re-opened.
叛乱的凯尔特人必须一次解决 斩草除根
These rebel Celts need to be dealt with once and for all.
这旨令要明确传达到各领地
This entire territory requires a clear and well-defined message.
是 科佛斯护民官
Yes,Tribune Corvus.
不
No!
杀掉他们
Kill them.
格杀勿论
Kill them all.
朗蒂尼亚姆
不列颠尼亚 罗马行省
17年后
真没用
Useless!
你把我从温柔乡拖来 就为看这个？
You've dragged me from a perfectly adequate brothel for this?
我想不通 凯撒为何中意这种狗窝
What Caesar saw in this hell hole,I'll never know.
养这些色雷斯人代价太昂贵
These Thracians are far too costly to feed.
他们老是和警卫过不去
They're always maiming the guards.
我在寻找新的 贝雷特
I'm looking for something new,Bellator,
新鲜的血液
something fresh.
大家叫他凯尔特人
They call him The Celt.
他的族人都是驯马高手 他是唯一幸存者
They say his people were horsemen and that he is the last of them.
凯尔特人 凯尔特人
Celt! Celt! Celt!
这人留在乡下浪费了吧 主人？
Wasted out here in the provinces,wouldn't you say,Master?
不列颠尼亚 朗蒂尼亚姆
庞贝城
让路 快让路
Make way! Make way!
离开道路 闪开
Off! Off the road! Off!
离开道路
Off the road!
让路给上等人
Make way for your betters!
快走 人渣
Move it,scum!
离开道路
Clear the way there!
快走
Move!
那匹马
The horse.
回去 奴隶
Back in line,slave!
马也会痛 你这无知的猪
The horse is in pain,you ignorant pig!
住手
Stop!
让他去帮帮那匹马
Let him help the horse.
是 小姐
Yes,My Lady.
放松 别怕 孩子
Easy. Easy,boy.
压住前腿上方 这样它断气时才不会痛苦
Put pressure on the top of the leg here,so he doesn't feel the pain when I move him.
抱歉 小姐 他是野蛮人
I'm sorry,My Lady. He's a savage.
起来
Get up!
换一匹马
Harness another horse.
为何那个粗人要杀马？
Why would the brute do that?
因为那是最仁慈的做法
Because it was the kindest thing to do.
走吧
Come.
谢谢
Thank you.
快走
Go on!
在罗马一整年 从没见你看过别的男人
A whole year in Rome and I never saw you look at any man
用看那奴隶的眼神
the way you looked at that slave.
我不敢相信他的力量
I can't believe he had the strength to do that.
你没看见他的肌肉吗？
Didn't you see his muscles?
- 我不是那个意思 - 真的？
- That's not what I meant. - Really?
别逗我了
Please...
你看 就在那里
Look. There it is.
我们到家了
We're home.
庞贝城
维纳丽亚酒神节
车夫 怎么了？
Driver,what is it?
维纳丽亚节 小姐
The Vinalia,My Lady.
街道堵住了 人太多了
The streets are blocked. Drunkards everywhere.
- 干嘛？- 走吧
- What? - Come on.
小姐？
My Lady?
小姐
My Lady!
- 我们逛逛 回家见 - 小姐
- We'll meet you back at the villa. - My Lady!
我记得这每座雕像 每个街角
I remember every statue,every street corner.
会使你想念罗马吗？
Does it make you miss Rome?
会使我忘记那里
It makes me forget it.
凯西雅 真高兴见到你
Cassia,it's so good to see you.
你怎么回来了？我们以为节庆后你才会回来
But how are you here? We weren't expecting you until after Vinalia.
我在罗马一天也呆不下去
I couldn't bear to spend another day in Rome.
太多傲慢的人巴结奉承你
Too many arrogant men who flatter you with their presence.
听起来我的宝贝长大了
It sounds like my baby is no longer a child.
爸 你哭了吗？
Father,are you crying?
别说出去 否则我会很没面子的
Tell no one. Or I'll never haggle a decent price again.
我们好想你
We missed you.
不得了 这全是你的行李？
Juno's tit! Is this all your luggage?
你是买下整座罗马城吗？
What have you done,purchase the entire city of Rome?
遇到心上人吗？
Did you meet anyone there?
- 跟庞贝城比 没人值得一提 - 嘿 别担心
- Nobody worth talking about in Pompeii. - Well,not to worry.
我想你父亲已经昭告全城的单身汉 为你准备欢迎宴会去了
I think your father has informed every unmarried man in the city of your return.
不会吧 真的？
Oh,no. Really?
快来 我要听听有关罗马的一切
Now,come on. I want to hear everything about Rome.
我好想你
I've missed you.
欢迎到你们的新家 野蛮人
Welcome to your new home,savages.
继续走
Keep walking!
站住
Stop!
解开他们
Unlock them.
喂这些畜牲
Feed these animals.
弗尔斯
Vires!
我好想你
I missed you.
我好想你 你好
I missed you. Hello.
它见到你很高兴 小姐
He's pleased to see you,My Lady.
我看得出它受到良好照顾 谢谢你 菲力克斯
And I can see he's been in good hands. Thank you,Felix.
明天一早我会把弗尔斯准备好 交给您
And I'll have Vires ready for you first thing tomorrow.
- 今晚我会亲自训练他 - 谢谢你
- I'll exercise him myself tonight. - Thank you.
我们明天见
I'll see you tomorrow.
阿提卡斯
Atticus...
这就是那个凯尔特人了
I think that's The Celt.
哪个凯尔特？
Which Celt?
独一无二的凯尔特人
The Celt.
听说他比你还快
They say that Celt is faster even than you.
他们总那么说
They always say that.
他要你报上名字 凯尔特人
He wants to know your name,Celt.
报上名字 你杀了他兄弟
He wants the name of the man who killed his brother.
他要我报上名字？
He wants to know my name?
两杯酒押色雷斯大汉
Two wine rations on the big Thracian.
两杯酒 成交
Two wine rations. Done.
给我解释
Explain.
不是他起头的 他正在用餐
He did not start it. He was trying to eat.
贝雷特
Bellator!
你得职责是看好这些人 懂吗？
Your purpose is to care for these men,is it not?
要是没人付钱观赏 别平白让他们自相残杀
Having them bite pieces from one another is of no value if no one is paying to see it.
抱歉 葛雷克斯主人
I'm sorry,Master Graecus.
那个没用了
That one is done.
这个
This one...
还有救
Can be repaired.
再有下次 贝雷特 你要付出代价
And the next time,Bellator,it will be at your cost.
我会记住你 凯尔特人
I'll remember you,Celt.
打开门
Open the gate!
关上
Close it!
你欠我两杯酒 凯尔特人
You owe me two wine rations,Celt.
渴吗？好吧
Thirsty? Okay.
怎么了？
What's wrong?
弗尔斯
Vires!
醒醒 人渣
Wake up,scum.
站起来
On your feet.
别紧张
Relax.
要是我想杀你 凯尔特人
If I was going to kill you,Celt...
我早就下手了
I would have done it already.
你叫什么名字？
What is your name?
我们迟早要交谈的
We will have to speak at some point.
没必要
No,we don't.
我们只是迟早要杀掉对方
What we have to do is kill each other at some point.
所以别管我的名字 我也没兴趣打听你的名字
So my name's my own,I have no interest in learning yours.
所有人出来
Everyone out!
快走
Move!
你老了 阿提卡斯
You're getting old,Atticus.
很多新来的 等不及要取代冠军
Plenty of young flesh out here just aching to take apart a champion.
明天我在竞技场再获胜 就是自由人了
When I win in the arena tomorrow,I'm a free man.
罗马法律规定的
It's Roman law.
你 无可奈何了
And there's nothing you can do about it.
阿提卡斯 我的冠军
Atticus,my champion,
明天你有幸 压轴上场比赛
tomorrow you have the honor of closing the games.
首先
First,
来看看 给你找了个旗鼓相当的对手
let us see if I have found an opponent worthy of you.
我看看…
Now...
哪个可怜虫该为我的自由而死？
Who's the poor bastard who has to die for my freedom?
不幸呀 凯尔特人
Unlucky,Celt.
太不幸
Very unlucky.
但我不会出手太重
But I'm going to take it easy on you.
给你个明天一试身手机会
Give you a fighting chance for tomorrow.
你小有名气 但没遇过我这种角斗士吧
You may have earned your reputation,but not fighting against a gladiator like me.
你的破绽太明显
You made that a little too obvious.
你破绽不明显么？
Did I make that too obvious?
贝雷特
Bellator!
让开
Get away!
别挡路 起来 人渣
Get out of the way! Get up,scum!
回去
Back to work!
你为什么救我？
Why did you save my life?
角斗士 不该死于暗算
No gladiator should die from a blade to the back.
要死 也要面对对手
When you die,the blow will come from the front.
我保证明天就是你死期
I promise it will be tomorrow.
我会亲手证明
And it will come from my hand.
我能给你更好的保证
Well,I can make you a better promise.
到那时
When the time comes,
你会死得很快
your death will be quick.
我会亲手证明
And it will come from my hand.
别担心 你的计划完美无瑕
Don't worry. Your plan is nothing short of brilliance.
只有疯子才会劝阻皇帝投资
Only a mad man would advise the Emperor against investing.
但愿皇帝不会派来疯子
Well,let us hope that the Emperor has not sent us one.
议员 原谅我们无法去港口接您
Senator,do forgive us for not being able to receive you at the harbor.
赛佛勒斯 你是大忙人 我完全谅解
Severus,you're a busy man. I understand entirely.
再说如果我有像你这种娇妻
Besides,if I had a wife as beautiful as yours,
我一定不急着离开她身边
I'd be in no hurry to forsake her company.
我是昆塔斯·科佛斯议员
I am Senator Quintas Attius Corvus.
愿神明容我为你们的款待祈福
May the gods grace me to bless your kind hospitality.
您太客气了 议员
You're most welcome,Senator.
议员 告诉我们罗马的消息
So,Senator,tell us the news from Rome.
新皇帝提图斯即位顺利吗？
How does the new emperor,Titus,fare?
"新"皇帝？
The "new" emperor?
新皇帝提图斯很顺利
The new emperor,Titus,fares well.
他的父亲 维斯帕先 受到人民爱戴
His father,Vespasian,was loved by his people,
自然会爱屋及乌
and they continue that love for his son.
- 正如神旨 - 确实
- As the gods demand? - Indeed.
赛佛勒斯 我想向你请教
Severus,I have a question for you.
我从港口到这里
On my journey from the harbor,
我注意到有些镇民背对着我
I noticed some of your townsfolk turned their backs towards me.
这不会有什么问题吧？
There wouldn't be some kind of problem,would there?
当地人怨恨罗马？
Some local resentment against Rome?
不 不成问题
No. Nothing of the sort.
只有少数 弱势力反对我们的计划
A tiny... A miniscule minority of opposition to our plans.
但我们的新建筑 会采用新式沟渠 将向人民证明一切
But our new construction will provide the people with a new aqueduct,
良好的卫生状况 更大的浴场
better sanitation,bigger bath houses,
新的竞技场
a new arena.
崭新的庞贝城
A whole new Pompeii.
讲新皇帝不恰当吗？
What was all that about the new emperor?
他是政客 你跟他说话要小心
He's a politician. Be careful what you say to him.
你想我们能跟他做生意吗？
Do you think we can do business with him?
如果皇帝没兴趣 他就不会来了
He wouldn't be here if the Emperor wasn't interested.
爸爸为什么邀请罗马议员来家里？
Why would father invite a Roman senator into our home?
你怎么能容忍这种事？
How could you allow such a thing?
想要罗马富豪来投资
If we want Rome's rich to spend their money here,
就得依照他们的要求
we must keep up with what they demand.
他们的要求？
What they demand?
爸爸不知道罗马的现况吗？
Does father have any idea what's going on in Rome right now?
自从提图斯掌权 一切都走样了
Since Titus took power,everything has changed.
皇帝只听小人的话
Every crooked man now has the ear of the Emperor.
他们自认能为所欲为
And they assume that they can take whatever they want.
凯西雅 你为什么提早回家？
Cassia,why did you come home early?
罗马发生什么事？
What happened in Rome?
我只是受够了
I'd simply had my fill of it.
母亲 是弗尔斯？
Mother,is that Vires?
冷静 冷静
Easy! Easy!
弗尔斯 你来这里干嘛？
Vires,what are you doing out here?
菲力克斯在哪里？
Where's Felix?
我听说明天是你的最后一战
I heard tomorrow is your last fight.
没错
That's right.
杀了你之后 他们就会给我自由
After I kill you,they will give me my freedom.
别作梦了
They won't do it.
你这么强 他们不会放你
Not while your arm's still strong.
自由是罗马的承诺
Freedom is Rome's promise.
你相信他们会履行承诺？
You trust them to keep that promise?
我相信他们的法律
I trust their law.
角斗士只有一种自由
There's only one freedom for a gladiator.
死在竞技场时 不屈不挠
When you die in that arena,you die unconquered.
当面唾弃罗马
And you spit in the eye of Rome.
那就是你的未来
Then this is your future.
你会以奴隶身分领死
And you die a slave.
我可不同
But not me.
明天罗马会信守承诺
Tomorrow,Rome will make good on its promise.
可惜你不会活着见证我是对的
You,unfortunately,will not be alive to see that I am right.
这么有自信？
So sure?
今天 你暴露了你的弱点
Today you showed me your weaknesses.
你的左臂没右臂有力
Your left arm is weaker than your right.
所以 你为了保护肋骨 暴露了脖子
So you protect your ribs at the expense of your neck.
那你变换重心时 该加强攻击力量
And you should learn how to thrust when you're shifting your weight
也别再偏重上方防卫
and stop favoring a high guard.
那样 你就不会那么好预测
It would make you less predictable.
这个
This one.
那个
That one.
这两个
These two.
站起来 奴隶们
On your feet,slaves.
好
All right.
你站这里
You,here.
你 野蛮人 站这里
You,barbarian,here!
两个都是一流的斗士
Both excellent fighters.
一个是冠军
One,a champion,
另一个在乡下经过考验和鉴定
and the other,tried and proven in the provinces.
我要看他的后面
I want to see him from behind.
干嘛这么严肃？
Why so serious?
这种夜班不错嘛
Not so bad for a night's work.
很结实
Firm.
但"武器"持久吗？
But what of his weaponry?
想一窥究竟 可得付钱
That is an inspection you'll have to pay for.
这会是新的竞技场 特别为战车竞赛设计
And this will be the new arena,specifically designed for chariot races.
好
Yes.
很详细 赛佛勒斯
Very detailed,Severus.
但我想这个计划不适合帝国投资
But I don't believe that this project is really suitable for an Imperial investment.
皇帝对这种乡间嬉戏没兴趣
These dalliances in the countryside hold very little interest for the Emperor.
我听到传闻…
I was led to understand...
不 很遗憾 皇帝的未来愿景 是集中在罗马
No. No. Unfortunately,the Emperor's vision for the future is firmly fixed on Rome.
我倒是有兴趣投资
I,however,am interested in investing.
很好
Good.
把合约拟好
Have the pledges drawn up.
明天比赛后 我就会签字
You'll have my mark on them tomorrow. After your games.
想必接下来该喝酒了
I do believe a drink is in order.
当然 我们加入宾客 好吗？
Of course. Shall we join our guests?
也许能带你女儿出来一见
Perhaps your daughter can bring it.
小女？
My daughter?
看那里
Look over there.
能跟马说话的奴隶
The slave who can talk to horses.
他真有男人味
He is a fine specimen.
好了 你不能否认
Well,you can't deny it.
转身
Turn around.
凯西雅
Cassia.
我能占用你一下时间吗？
May I impose upon you for a moment?
有位客人要求见你
Your presence has been requested.
当然 父亲
Yes,of course,Father.
拿着 但不是给你的
You will need this. it is not for you.
- 凯西雅 容我介绍…- 科佛斯议员
- Cassia,may I introduce... - Senator Corvus.
凯西雅小姐
Lady Cassia.
天啊 我好想你
My,how I have missed you.
你美极了
You are exquisite.
议员大人 我不知道该说什么
Senator Corvus,I don't know what to say.
给我的？真体贴
For me? How kind.
你们彼此认识？
You two have met?
赛佛勒斯 你还在啊
Severus,you're still here.
我不知道你认识小女
I did not know you knew my daughter.
那你该听听来龙去脉
Then you should hear the whole story.
明天在竞技场签约时再聊
Tomorrow in the arena when I sign your pledges.
谢谢
Thank you.
马库斯
Marcus?
议员和凯西雅在罗马就已相识
The Senator and Cassia have already met,in Rome.
那她需要个女伴
Then she requires a chaperone.
她没有我们 都能在罗马熬过一年
She survived a year in Rome without us.
这是在自家露台 她一定能应付这10分钟
I'm sure she can survive 10 minutes on our balcony.
在罗马 我以为我们已达成共识
In Rome,I thought we had an understanding.
不 是你一箱情愿
No. You had an understanding.
我没给你机会
One for which I gave you no cause.
你光是出现 就给了我机会 小姐
Your mere presence gives me cause,My Lady
像你这种美人 不该待在这种假日胜地
A beauty such as yours has no place in a holiday resort like this.
当然像你这种尤物 只属于永恒之城
Surely,a creature such as you can have no home but in the Eternal City.
议员 我根本不想回罗马去
Senator,I have no intention of returning to Rome.
倘若是以我妻子的身份回去呢？
And if you were to return as my wife?
你妻子？
Your wife?
你也许当作是恭维
You may consider it a compliment.
科佛斯议员 我想你误会我是那些
Senator Corvus,I believe you have mistaken me
女人 在罗马坐你大腿的那种
for the kind of woman who drapes herself across your lap in Rome.
我也不愿成为你的妻子
I have no wish to become your wife.
断然拒绝 如我所料
A spirited refusal. I would have expected nothing less.
好好享受维纳丽亚节的尾声吧 晚安
Enjoy the remains of the Vinalia,Senator. Good night.
这样正常吗？
Is this normal?
是火山 时不时会有抱怨
It is the mountain. It grumbles from time to time.
把这个人带来 我需要他
Bring this man. I need him.
- 小姐 - 马上
- My Lady... - Now!
小姐 是弗尔斯
My Lady,it's Vires!
拜托 免得它伤了自己
Please,before he injures himself.
我得单独进去
I have to go in alone.
不行
No.
让他进去
Let him.
小姐 他是野蛮人
My Lady,he's a savage.
让他进去
Let him.
冷静
Easy!
小姐 他很危险
My Lady,he's not safe.
让开
Move.
在外面等
Wait outside.
你怎么做到的？
How did you do that?
我问过他
I asked him.
你在成为角斗士前 就会骑马？
You could ride before you were a gladiator?
我在会走路前 就会骑马
I could ride before I could walk.
我的族人都 曾经是驯马高手
My people were horsemen.
"曾经是"？
"Were" horsemen?
我的家人被罗马人赶尽杀绝
My family were butchered by the Romans.
- 很遗憾 - "遗憾"？
- I'm so sorry. - "Sorry"?
罗马人哪会懂这些些？
What would a Roman know of such things?
我不是罗马人 我是庞贝公民
I am not a Roman. I'm a citizen of Pompeii.
为何罗马的鹰旗到处可见？
Then why do I see Rome's eagle everywhere I turn?
这跟我无关
I'm no part of that.
在罗马待一年后 我再也不想看那面鹰旗了
After a year in Rome,I hoped never to see that eagle again.
然而 这也有了 已经渗透到我家门外
And yet,here it is,thrust into the soil outside my home.
家父相信他能跟那些禽兽协议
My father believes that he can bargain with those animals.
换作我爸
My father...
会将他们诛尽杀绝
He would have killed every last one of them.
小姐？
My Lady?
他们逮到你骑在马上会惩罚你
If they catch you up there they'll punish you.
小姐？
My Lady?
小姐 一切还好吗？
My Lady,is everything all right?
等等 回来
Wait! Come back!
回来
Come back!
怎么了？
What's wrong?
万一他们逮到你跟我在这里
If they catch you up here with me...
我会说 是我自愿
I'll tell them it was my choice.
他们在那里
There they are!
我得送你回去
I have to take you back.
不 你走 留下我
No. You go and leave me here.
你骑走它 这是个机会
If you ride you have a chance.
- 什么机会？- 自由
- A chance at what? - At freedom.
但你要付出什么代价？
But at what cost to you?
告诉警卫 我强行带你来这里
Tell the guards I brought you here by force.
把责任归咎于我
The blame is mine.
把他拖下来
Get him off that horse!
不是他的错 马脱缰逃走 失控了
It wasn't his fault. The horse bolted. It was out of control.
议员 拜托 这奴隶救了我一命
Senator,please. This slave saved my life.
他不该被处决
He does not deserve this.
- 凯西雅小姐 你没受伤吧？- 我毫发无损
- Lady Cassia,you were unharmed? - I'm perfectly all right.
要我放这奴隶一条生路 你怎么报答我？
If I were to spare the life of this slave,what would it be worth to you?
议员？
Senator?
想必你明白这个问题 亲爱的
I believe you understand the question,my dear.
我会很感激你的慈悲
I would be grateful for your mercy.
好吧
Well...
今天你走运 奴隶 凯西雅小姐救了你的小命
This is your lucky day,slave. The Lady Cassia has saved your life.
这奴隶是谁的？
Who owns this slave?
我的 议员
I do,Senator.
那我建议你杀一儆百 然后放了
Then I suggest you punish it and then remove it.
15鞭应该足够
Fifteen lashes should suffice.
毕竟 慈悲是一种美德
After all,mercy is a virtue.
父亲 你得制止
Father,you have to stop this.
我爱莫能助
There's nothing I can do about it.
你救了他一命
You saved his life.
你已该庆幸
Content yourself with that.
科佛斯议员有求于你
Senator Corvus requires a service of you.
我？
Of me?
这个角斗士
This gladiator.
你明天对他有何安排？
What do you have planned for him tomorrow?
他最后上场
He fights last.
- 跟我的冠军单打独斗 - 不行
- Single combat against my champion. - No.
他最先上场 得先送死
He fights first. And he dies first.
他被鞭15下都没吭一声
Fifteen lashes and he didn't make a sound.
我原本能阻止这一切
I could have prevented this.
我乱了思绪
I don't know what I was thinking.
他让你感到活力
That he made you feel alive?
他让我感到安全
He made me feel safe.
那种男人不应当死在竞技场
A man like that does not deserve to die in the arena.
这不是你的错 凯西雅
This is not your fault,Cassia.
他激怒议员了
He has caught the Senator's wrath.
我以为离开罗马 那个人会忘记我
I thought that,in leaving Rome,that man would forget about me
转而觊觎别的倒霉鬼
and turn his attentions toward some other poor victim.
今晚我看到他的眼神 阿丽德妮
I saw a look in that man's eye tonight,Ariadne.
跟我在罗马看到的一样
The same look I saw in Rome.
但议员从未染指你？
But the Senator never laid a hand on you.
幸好我在他动手前离开罗马
Only because I left Rome before he could.
现在他从罗马跟随我们 到了庞贝
Now Rome has followed us back to Pompeii
会搞得天翻地覆
to turn the world inside out.
你真懂得准备比赛
You certainly know how to prepare for a battle.
希望她是值得的
I hope she was worth it.
糟蹋了好酒
A terrible waste of good wine.
你能感觉到吗？
Can you feel that?
是诸神
It is the gods.
- 他们对芸芸众生自有安排 - 也许吧
- They have a plan for us all. - Perhaps.
什么意思？
What do you mean?
今晚我看到杀死我全家的人
Tonight I saw the man who killed my whole family.
也许诸神让我存活有其理由
Perhaps the gods spared me for a reason.
20年前罗马人夺走我的家人
The Romans took my family from me 20 years ago.
每晚 我努力回想他们的面孔 但我想不起来
At night I try and remember their faces,but I cannot.
但我知道总有一天 神会让我找到他们
But I know one day,the gods will bring me to them again.
我叫米洛
My name is Milo.
阿提卡斯
Atticus.
你 那个隧道
You,that tunnel.
把凯尔特人送进那个隧道
Send The Celt into that tunnel.
我以为他要跟阿提卡斯对打
I thought he was to fight Atticus.
- 你有新的指示 - 是 主人
- You're being given new instructions. - Yes,Master.
那阿提卡斯和谁打？
And Atticus?
他照常单打独斗
He'll fight single combat as billed.
让他跟斯巴达大汉对打 给观众一场精彩比赛
Put him with the big Spartan. He'll give the audience a good show.
那阿提卡斯会打败他赢得自由
And Atticus will beat him and win his freedom.
观众真的想看到这一幕？
Is that really what the audience will want to see?
你想说什么？
What are you saying?
不觉得他们宁可看到 角斗士赴死而不是苟活？
Don't you think they'd rather see a gladiator meeting death rather than life?
尤其是死得光荣？
Especially a death as glorious as his?
站住
Stop.
你
You.
那边
That way.
你也是 野蛮人
You too,barbarian.
科佛斯议员
Senator Corvus.
凯西雅小姐
Lady Cassia.
过来坐我身边
Come sit beside me.
用你的智慧为我增光
Give me the benefit of your wisdom.
喜欢看这种竞赛吗？
Do YOU enjoy the sports?
看人互相残杀为乐 不算竞赛
Men killing each other for our amusement is not a sport.
到处都是 全是新裂痕
Everywhere. All new.
我没空跟你扯 葛雷克斯 你在暗示什么？
I don't have time for this,Graecus. What are you suggesting?
取消比赛？
That we cancel the games?
当然不是 只是延后
Of course not. Merely postpone them.
这座竞技场已矗立一百年
This amphitheater has stood for a hundred years.
禁得起大地震
It withstood the great earthquake.
可能不安全 睁亮眼
It may not be safe. Use your eyes.
声明在先 有什么事我可无法负责
I'm just saying I cannot be held responsible for what may happen.
那就不要理会 我负全责
Then don't be. I take full responsibility.
我们哪能期望 罗马托付我们重建整座城市
How can we expect Rome to trust us to rebuild an entire city
如果我们办不成简单的角斗？
if we can't stage a simple bloody spectacle?
拿我的行囊来
Fetch my litter.
我要出城几天
I'm leaving town for a few days.
快走
Move.
站住 铐住他们
Stop. Shackle them!
这是干嘛？
What is this?
这是你最伟大的时刻 阿提卡斯
This is your greatest moment,Atticus.
你在竞技场的末日
Your final day in the arena.
我应该要单挑的
I'm supposed to fight single combat.
给他们武器
Bring them their weapons!
祝好运 阿提卡斯
Good fortune,Atticus.
赴死者 我们向你们致敬
To those about to die,we salute you!
由马库斯·赛佛勒主持 献给提图斯皇帝的盛世
By the patronage of Marcus Cassius Severus and for the glory of Emperor Titus,
并特此谨记 科佛斯议员的非凡胜利
remember,all here,the mighty victory of Senator Quintas Attius Corvus
和他铲平凯尔特人叛乱的功迹
and his annihilation of the Celtic Rebellion.
凯尔特人叛乱？
The Celtic Rebellion?
您为了帝国的伟大和高贵胜利
Your great and noble victory for the Empire,Senator,
重开北方贸易路线
re-opening the northern trade routes.
史书会记下您的壮举
The history books record it as your finest hour.
我想您应该也想要光荣开赛
I thought perhaps you might like the honor of opening these games in a similar manner.
赛佛勒斯 我受宠若惊了
Severus,you flatter me.
我们会让你享有罗马人的殊荣
We'll make a Roman out of you yet.
庞贝的子民
People of Pompeii!
愿朱比特和维纳斯 保佑维纳丽亚节并颂扬比赛
May Jupiter and Venus bless the Vinalia and honor these games!
竞赛开始
Let the games begin!
- 这不是格斗 - 什么？
- This isn't a battle. - What?
这是一场屠杀
This is a massacre.
你怎么知道？
How do you know?
因为我是过来人
Because I was there.
反叛的凯尔特人正在撤离
The rebel Celts are in retreat,
留下强暴 杀戮尾随而至
leaving rape and slaughter in their wake,
返回遭亵渎的巢穴 饱尝无辜受害者的血肉
returning to their unholy lair to feast on the flesh of their innocent victims.
这就是你们受训的目的 人渣
This is what you've trained for,scum.
赶快出来
Now get out there.
昆塔斯·科佛斯 给他们投降的机会
Quintas Attius Corvus gave them every chance to surrender.
但慈悲对野蛮人来说是陌生概念
But mercy was an alien concept to these savages,
怀抱沉重的心 昆塔斯·科佛斯
and with heavy heart,Quintas Attius Corvus
下令他的强大军团 以皇帝之名攻击
ordered his mighty legions,in the name of the Emperor,to attack.
举盾
Shields up!
推进
Push!
你称这是所谓的竞赛？
Is this what you call sport?
不 小姐 这不是竞赛 这是政治
No,Lady Cassia,this is not sport. This is politics.
我们挡不住他们
We can't hold them!
后退
Back!
赛佛勒斯 我记得不该是这样
Severus,this is not exactly how I remember it.
那奴隶对你有何意义？
What exactly is that slave to you?
跟你南辕北辙 议员
Everything that you are not,Senator.
那你该很高兴得知
Then you should be pleased to learn
令尊已把你许配给我
your father has granted me your hand in marriage.
- 什么？- 我没做过这种约定
- What? - I made no such arrangement.
因为他知道要是拒绝了
Because he knows that if he does not,
我会通报提图斯皇帝 令尊质疑
I will inform Titus that your father has called into question
"新"皇帝的统治能力
our "new" emperor's ability to rule.
皇帝会把你全家吊死在城墙
Titus will have your entire family hung from the city walls.
米洛
Milo!
如果我要嫁给你
If I were to marry you...
- 凯西雅 - 如果我嫁给你
- Cassia... - If I marry you,
我的家人能免于一死吗？
is my family spared?
你的家人就会成为我的家人
Your family will become my family,
受到皇帝的保护
under the protection of the Emperor.
并拥有各种附带优势
With all of the benefits that that implies.
庞贝 庞贝 庞贝
Pompeii! Pompeii! Pompeii!
议员
Senator!
我不会屈服于罗马的力量
I do not yield to the power of Rome!
我唾弃它
I spit on it!
量他没这个胆
He would not dare.
庞贝 庞贝 庞贝
Pompeii! Pompeii! Pompeii!
加派士兵进入竞技场 马上
Get a detachment in the arena now.
快去
Now!
你说的对 兄弟
You were right,brother.
他们承诺的一切全是谎言
Everything they promised,nothing but lies.
赦免 赦免 赦免 赦免
Live! Live! Live!
你到底想干嘛？
What do you think you're doing?
夫人 坐好
Madame,take your seat!
想活命就给我坐下
If you want to live you will sit down!
马上
Now!
如果你现在杀他
If you kill him now,
万箭齐发 他会变成烈士而不是暴民
on the tip of 100 Roman arrows,you make him a martyr to the mob.
你想要那样？
Is that what you want?
给皇帝带回一场革命？
To take home to your Emperor a revolution?
况且如果你推翻这个决定 那罗马的承诺属实吗？
And if you reverse this decision,how will it be spoken of in Rome?
大家会闲言闲语
They will whisper it behind your back,
说你妻子不顺从你
that you have a wife who does not obey your will.
你的名声能承受这种污点？
Can your reputation bear such a weakness?
我可能成为你的妻子 但你绝对得不到我的人
I might become your wife,but you will never break me.
我会得到你的
But I will break you,
你会温驯到站坐爬都唯我是从
and you will stay broken to stand,sit or crawl as I decree.
听清楚了吗？
Do you understand me?
普罗克路斯 派人把她带回家
Proculus,have your guard take her back to the villa.
把她关在那里
Keep her there.
我想婚礼应该在罗马举行
I think the wedding shall be in Rome.
庞贝的子民
People of Pompeii!
火神说话了
Vulcan speaks!
火神裁定那个人是庞贝的冠军
Vulcan decrees that man to be the champion of Pompeii!
他值得挺身当面对抗罗马强权
Decrees that he is worthy to stand face-to-face against the might of Rome!
伟大的火神 我们听到您说话并会遵循
Great Vulcan,we hear you speak and will obey!
普罗克路斯
Proculus...
让这些懦夫见识
Show these cowards what really happens
胆敢挑战罗马强权的下场
when you dare to challenge the might of Rome.
乐意之至
With pleasure.
快点 快点
Come on! Come on!
快走
Faster! Move it!
怎么回事？小姐？
What's going on? My Lady?
别碰她 放开她
Don't touch her! Let her go!
凯西雅
Cassia!
由昆塔斯·科佛斯议员主持
By the patronage of Senator Quintas Attius Corvus,
罗马的冠军 马库斯·普罗克路斯
the champion of Rome,Marcus Proculus,
歼灭凯尔特人的英雄
hero of the Celtic Rebellion,
现在会面对庞贝的新冠军 凯尔特人
will now face the new champion of Pompeii,The Celt,
单打独斗
in single combat!
提图斯皇帝万岁
All hail to Emperor Titus!
我认识你
I know you.
真的？
Really?
无论你想报什么仇
Well,whatever revenge you think you're going to have,
恐怕你会失望
I'm afraid you'll be disappointed.
给这奴隶像样的剑
Bring this slave a better sword.
- 刀刃是钝的 - 是吗？
- This blade's dull. - Is it?
给大家看一场好戏吧
Let's give them a good show,huh?
杀了他
Kill him!
快杀了他
Kill him now!
不
No!
你很勇敢 我很佩服
You're brave. I'll give you that.
但野蛮人绝对敌不过罗马人
But no savage could ever be the match for a Roman.
那我们20人呢？
How about 20 of us?
不要
No!
等等 等等
Wait! Wait!
不要
No!
怜悯我
Mercy!
不要
No!
很高兴见到你 兄弟
Good to see you,brother.
我也是
And you.
欧蕾莉亚
Aurelia.
杀了他
Kill him.
经过再三考虑 我决定不投资你的小城市
On further consideration,I have decided not to invest in your little city.
送我到港口
Get me to the harbor.
对不起
I'm sorry.
让开 让开
Move. Move it!
你  过来这里
You! Come here!
我的船费
For my passage.
让他上船
Let him aboard.
你们要赶快离开
You must leave now!
起锚 准备启航
Cast off! Prepare to set sail!
救命 救命
Help me! Please!
你…
You...
你一定要帮助我们
You have to help us.
你一定要救凯西雅
You have to save Cassia.
她在哪里？
Where is she?
家里
The villa.
- 你要去哪里？- 我要去找她
- Where are you going? - I have to find her.
米洛 别异想天开了
Milo,this is madness!
我们要去港口 找艘船
We have to get to the harbor and find a boat.
火山会烧死所有人
The mountain is going to kill us all!
她为了我冒生命危险 阿提卡斯 为了我不顾一切
She risked her life for me,Atticus. Risked everything for me!
没有她 我们早就死在竞技场
Without her,they would have killed us in that arena!
那我们一起去
Then we will go together.
不行
No.
你获得了你的自由 我的朋友
You have your freedom,my friend.
现在她是我的目标
Now she is mine.
那我们在港口碰面
Then we meet at the harbor.
港口见
At the harbor.
拜托 给我钥匙
Please,give me the keys!
凯西雅 他们拿走了钥匙
Cassia,they've taken the keys!
不
No!
她在哪里？
Where is she?
拿水来
Water!
你回来找我
You came back for me.
喝吧 喝吧
Drink. Drink.
谢谢 姊妹
Thank you,sister.
不要
No!
看着我
Look at me.
我们要赶去港口
We have to get to the harbor.
这样是自杀 回头 回去
This is suicide. Turn around! Back!
让路
Out of the way!
Get out of the way!
够了
Enough!
杀了他们 杀光他们
Kill them! Kill them all!
快划 白痴 快划
Row,you idiots! Row!
回头 你们得回头
Turn around! You have to turn back!
起来 起来
Come on. Get up! Get up!
不 不  我的女儿
No! No,my daughter!
起来
Get up!
不
No!
我的女儿
My daughter!
妈妈 救我
Mommy! Help!
这是世界末日吗？
Is this the end of the world?
为何神会让这种事发生？
Why would the gods let this happen?
- 米洛 - 阿提卡斯
- Milo! - Atticus!
我知道诸神绝对抓不到你
I knew the gods would never catch you.
你太快了 现在我懂原因了
There's none faster. And now I see why.
- 该走了 我的朋友 - 不行
- It's time to go,my friend... - No.
港口不见了 我们得另找出路
The harbor's gone. We have to find another way.
那我们往南进入丘陵
Then we have to go south into the hills.
太远了 我们走路到不了
It's too far. We'll never make it on foot.
那我们去那里
Then we go there.
竞技场？为什么？
The arena? Why?
有马
Horses.
我的父母
My parents.
我去牵马
I'll get the horses.
别去
Don't.
去帮你朋友
Go help your friend.
阿提卡斯 在吗？
Atticus?
到处是罗马人
Romans everywhere.
走吧
Let's go.
你最好舒服待着 到罗马还很远
You better get comfortable,my dear. It's a long way to Rome.
你为何这样做？
Why are you doing this?
因为凡是我昆塔斯·科佛斯议员的资产
Because the property of Quintas Attius Corvus
不准被随便个奴隶抢去
will not be taken by some slave.
普罗克路斯 没你位子了
Proculus,there's not enough room for you.
那我们罗马见 议员
Then I shall see you in Rome,Senator.
科佛斯
Corvus!
我悬赏一千取那奴隶的人头
1,000 dinari to the man who brings me the head of that slave!
- 现在换我了 快去 - 阿提卡斯
- This is mine now. Go. - Atticus...
再不去就追不回她了
Every second takes her further away from you.
后会有期 兄弟
I'll see you again,brother.
挺住
Go on!
野蛮人死不足惜 不像罗马人
A barbarian does not die the equal of a Roman.
胡扯
Equal
来瞧瞧罗马人
Let's see if a Roman
跟角斗士决一死战的结果
can die the equal of a gladiator.
不要
No!
求求你 求求你
Please. Please.
角斗士不会乞求
Gladiators do not beg.
贱人 你这贱人
Bitch! You bitch!
等等 等等 等等
Wait! Wait! Wait!
你跟我有何深仇大恨？
Who are you to do this to me?
我是昆塔斯·科佛斯议员
I am Senator Quintas Attius Corvus!
那又怎样？昆塔斯·科佛斯议员
And what is that worth,Senator Quintas Attius Corvus?
你残杀我家人
You killed my family,
屠杀我族人 无庸置疑
you slaughtered my people,and make no mistake,
我的神让我来找你了
my gods are coming for you.
等等
Wait!
你不能把我留在这里
You can't leave me here!
赴死的同袍
For those of us about to die...
我们向你们致敬
We salute you!
我以自由之身死去
I die a free man!
你快把马骑走
You have to ride him out of here.
- 不要 - 它不够快
- No! - He's not fast enough.
载不了我们两人 快走
He can't carry us both! Go!
不要 我不会丢下你
No,I won't leave you!
我们别无选择
We don't have a choice.
快跑 快走
Run! Go!
我不愿浪费最后相聚的一刻去逃命
I don't want to spend our last moments running.
别看
Don't look.
看着我
Look at me.
只要看着我
Just me.